<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Euaggelion aionuon tes oukoumenes tes mellouses, or, The saints first revealed and covenanted mercies shortly approaching as being the main scope of revelation-prophesie : opened and resolved by Christ's divine key of prophesie ... / by W. Sherwin ...</title>
            <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34223</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14150914</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14150914</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102109</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A71021)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102109)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1070:6 or 1070:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Euaggelion aionuon tes oukoumenes tes mellouses, or, The saints first revealed and covenanted mercies shortly approaching as being the main scope of revelation-prophesie : opened and resolved by Christ's divine key of prophesie ... / by W. Sherwin ...</title>
                  <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 18 p., [1] leaf of plates : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First six words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>1070:6 lacks portrait frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>Duplicate copies appear at reel position 1070:6 and 7; 1070:6 incorrectly identified as Wing S3402.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Prophecies.</term>
               <term>Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102109:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102109:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, OR THE SAINTS FIRST REVEALED AND COVENANTED MERCIES, Shortly Approaching. As being the Main Scope of <hi>Revelation-Propheſie;</hi> Opened and Reſolved by <hi>Christ's Divine Key of Propheſie,</hi> in the four laſt Chapters thereof. In exceeding much Mercy lately Diſcovered to the Weak and Unworthy Pen-man of the enſuing Work, and eſpecially by the help of the more late and very Uſeful <hi>Key</hi> and <hi>Covenants,</hi> An. Dom. 71. with <hi>Parallels</hi> of <hi>Dan.</hi> and <hi>Rev.</hi> more directly leading us to the laſt ſaid great Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Explained in our laſt Books. And for the better Improvement of them all, here is prefixed a Summarie of the Cleareſt and moſt Aboundant Scripture-evidence of that Bleſſed State of the World to come. In Reference to a Scheme or ſhort Proſpective View of the Whole, from God's Word.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. Sherwin,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:102109:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102109:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Introduction to our Scheme or ſhort Proſpective View of the most ſtrong and clear evidence of the bleſſed ſtate of the</hi> 1000 <hi>Years,</hi> Rev. 20. <hi>as is manifeſt in our late Works.</hi> Shewing;</head>
            <p n="1">1. THat ſuch a ſtate ſhall be in the World in the ſeventh <hi>Millen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What that ſtate is declared to be from the Word of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Shewing in a fit Latitude the time when, or the neer approach of that ſaid ſtate.</p>
            <p n="4">4. How, or by what means it ſhall be ſet up.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Unto theſe we ſhall add ſomewhat of the Uſefulneſs of that excellent gracious Diſcovery thereof, chiefly from Parallelling <hi>Dan.</hi> and <hi>Rev.</hi> both in connexion of Matters and Times, as leading us to the fourth Gentile Monarchie, wherein Gods Kingdome of the Stone, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. was to be ſet up, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 34. for 1666. years from Chriſts Aſcention to his Deſcending again to break all adverſe Kingdomes and Dominions, until it ſelf become a Mountain, <hi>v.</hi> 34, 41. about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1700. with the allowance of Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhers</hi> four years loſt or more, and ſo probable to be ſooner.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt, three things are here to be done, firſt to prove (as in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, <hi>Iren. Chap.</hi> 1. the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, namely) to ſhew that ſuch a Sate or Kingdome ſhall be: which is abundantly proved in our ſaid work; firſt from the ſeven Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in our <hi>Irenic.,</hi> mentioned in the beginning thereof. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dly, From the other ſeven <hi>Convincing Arguments</hi> [beſides that Third] in the <hi>Word Written:</hi> all which are of very large comprehenſiveneſs; and if duly weighed, will be found to be of very great force: And all our Parallels of <hi>Danniel</hi> and <hi>Revelation</hi> do alſo very greatly eſtabliſh theſe Truths; all which we refer to the Judicious and Impartial Readers peruſal: together with the Twelve Foundations of our Faith thereof, proved all along from <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. to the end of the <hi>Revelation:</hi> which Faith was alſo much formed by our 31 Uſeful Obſervations to underſtand Myſtical Propheſies? and by the ſhort Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and uſeful and needful Diſtinctions in our <hi>Key:</hi> To the due conſideration of all which, we adviſe the ſerious reading of our Account of the whole Work, firſt more generally of the ſubject, p. 1, 2. and 2dly, of the Nature, Uſe and Order of the Parts of the ſaid Work, in <hi>page.</hi> 2, 3, 4. with the two firſt leaves of the General Title Page, or of the ſaid Twelve Foundations, and in the two firſt leaves of the laſt Book on <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. ſhewing what parts ſerve for Explication, what for Confirmation, and what for Illuſtration, and Application, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> page 1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, To ſhew this ſaid ſtate ſhall be in the World, which is ſufficiently done by our 15 well approved Reaſons by the Learned in thoſe Studies (to which many more may be added.) See our <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> on <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. page 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the moſt Certain, Infallible, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſistable farther Evidences.</head>
               <p>ANd now from Gods gracious late Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery to us that the ſaid bleſſed ſtate will be the fulfilling of his declared and Covenanted Mercies then in the ſaid ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth <hi>Millen.</hi> unto the Fathers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to their ſpiritual ſeed through and with that their own Divine Seed Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. and 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.16 to the end, as in our two laſt Books on <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. is largely explained, which Chriſts ſaid <hi>Revelation Key</hi> Divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opens, and which we endeavour here to the beſt advantage we can in a buſineſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102109:3"/>of this nature to communicate, ſo briefly, to all faithful Chriſtians herein concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and for all others who may be ſuch, by ſetting before all men, yet more ſtrong, clear, and irreſiſtable evidences from the word of God concerning the ſaid Mercies, as eternally decreed by God, &amp; after car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on in the ſaid Covenants &amp; Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of the Old Teſtament, &amp; witneſſed to through the New, to manifeſt how in the ſaid 7th Milen. as Chriſt by his <hi>Revel</hi> alſo hath infallibly reſolved us, that all ſhall anſwerably be done (as in good part was ſhewed) in our Picture of Chriſts moſt Divine Key, p. 63. of the Reſur. which I doubt not but will farther make the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences thereof ſo ſtrong, clear, and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtable, and (as I verily believe) of ſo great weight, as greater cannot be had to prove any Truth, (nor need to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected for theſe) and greater then for any other Truth in the whole book of God, this containing the ſumm of all, namely, Chriſts great work of Redemption, as the work ſo eternally appointed by the Father to be ſo carryed on by him in the time of his Mediatorſhip in the firſt ſix Millen. (as by and by we doubt not to prove) to redeem the ſouls, bodies, perſons, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward conditions of his Saints and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants then from the Power and Tyranny of their Enemies: &amp; the World &amp; Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in that ſtate from the Corruption, Curſe, Bondage Enmity in it ſince the Fall of Man, as in <hi>Reſtit.</hi> p 45, 46, 37, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereupon we muſt lay down this needful Caution by the way; <hi>viz.</hi> That we muſt diſtinguiſh the ſaid General work of Redemption, from that Spiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Powerful work of Reconciliation for his Saints at Chriſts firſt coming, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the warrant of the holy Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling us unto himſelf, and now by his word of Reconciliation.</hi> Rom. 5.10. <hi>When Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, we were reconciled to Grd by the death of his Son:</hi> and <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.16. <hi>That he might reconcile both Jew and Gentile in one body by the Croſs,</hi> &amp;c. Chriſt by his death ſo making an Attonement in his blood by his own oblation of himſelf once for all his people, and thereby laid the ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation at his firſt coming, for his power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and glorious carrying on of all the parts and degrees of the other (as being made the Fathers Commiſſioner) during his Kingdome of the Stone (whileſt he ſits upon his Fathers Throne) at that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous delivery of the Book with 7 Seals <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. to him the Lamb, with ſeven Hornes, and ſeven Eyes, to open, and execute the Contents thereof, unto <hi>chap</hi> 19. until his ſecond coming at the end of the ſaid 1666. years when he will ſit upon his own Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. for we cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe enough to that ſoul aſtoniſhing wonder, of Gods ſo free and gracious gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his only Son ſo to dye for ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to reconcile them to himſelf, yea God was in Chriſt ſo reconciling them (as ſaith the Apoſtle) to himſelf; nor of Chriſts Love and Compaſſion, ſo to reconcile them to God the Father by his own blood-ſhedding, all which were alſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by the powerful and glorious ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Lord the Spirit both for Chriſt, at firſt overſhaddowing the bleſſed Virgin at his holy Conception, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by the eternal ſpirit offered himſelf to God without ſpot, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24. &amp; at laſt by his Reſurrection, declaring him with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by the Spirit of Sanctification to be the Son of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. and by his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Saints at all times: which ſaid work of Reconciliation was to be the ſure and neceſſary foundation of all the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parts of the ſaid General Work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from Mans Fall to the end, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the greateſt extent, as it was Gods ſaid eternal Deſign by Chriſt ſo to carry on the ſaid Work in the ſaid time, which we ſhall here endeavour to ſet before the eyes and underſtandings of all ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Chriſtians for their exceeding great Conſolation and ſatisfaction (if duly pondered and improved) which will far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appear (as we ſaid) by the ſaid e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Decrees, Covenants and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102109:3"/>in the Old Teſtament, and the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſings of Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the New; but all moſt ſtrongly determined by Chriſts own moſt Divine Revelation But becauſe the firſt 6000 years appear to be alſo appointed by him for the carrying on of his Deſigne for that ſtate in the ſeventh <hi>Millennium,</hi> and therefore to run paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel with the ſaid decreed great work of the Redemption of the World, <hi>viz.</hi> both of Men and Creatures, (as we ſaid) we ſhall upon this third Particular, reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſts carrying it on in the fix firſt <hi>Millenniums</hi> to the ſeventh, conſider, what proof and evidence we find from the word of God for the ſame, which may double the ſtrength of the ſaid farther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Proofs which we are to proceed to ſpeak of; therefore we ſhall firſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the reality thereof from Scripture warrant, before we proceed to the other proofs thereof, (which will include much alſo of the condition of that ſaid ſtate from firſt to laſt) firſt the Holy Ghoſt excellently expoundeth them by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling of them to the ſix dayes of Creation, before God reſted the ſeventh day, and to the Type of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> reſt in <hi>Canaan</hi> under <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s conduct, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying thereby, that after 6000 years ſhould be Chriſts Sabbatiſme of reſt from ſuch his great work of Redemption: as the ſpirit of God explains both, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3, and 4 <hi>ch.</hi> which our Saviour likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth by his moſt ſure Revelation inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation thereof, and none like it.</p>
               <p>And 2dly, this is alſo done by God's Spirit comparing 1000 years to one day; as firſt from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. where 1000 years with God are ſaid to be as yeſterday, which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 Epiſt. 3.8. ſets forth with great Emphaſis, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares it to be a great point, which he would not have Chriſtians ignorant of, that one day with the Lord, [Chriſt] (whoſe coming he there ſpeaks of) is as 1000 years; and he puts it both wayes, ſaying, and 1000 years as one day; <hi>viz.</hi> in reference to his ſaid coming, to be at the end of the ſixth <hi>Millennium;</hi> and our Saviour alſo moſt exactly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termineth that Sabbatiſme of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth <hi>Millennium</hi> accordingly, by 1000 years ſix times over, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. of which more afterwards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Chriſts carrying on that ſaid work of Redemption for his Univerſal True Church, as that work which his Father gave him to do, in that reſpect, in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of his three great Offices in the time of his Mediatorſhip in the World, which was firſt in his eminent Prophetical Office in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>000 years to his firſt coming; and ſecondly in his eminent Prieſtly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the New Teſtament, in the next 2000 years, before the period of his emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Kingly Office for his ſaid Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal true Church will begin, in that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſtate in that world to come: (as is largely proved in our Treatiſe on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15)</p>
               <p n="4">4. This alſo may appear from that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Promiſe of Gods ſhewing mercy to 1000 Generations, that is, for the 7000 years of the worlds continuance: (as we reckon in the middle ſtate of things, three lives to be 21 years, as in page 6, and 7 of our <hi>Key</hi> is explained.)</p>
               <p n="5">5. From Scripture Chronologie, firſt of <hi>Moſes</hi> his 2400 years and more, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to him for time paſt, with what was in <hi>Joſhua, Judges, Kings</hi> and <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles,</hi> which Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> that very good man, and great Antiquary, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes at <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple built 3000 years, and at the Jews Captivity at <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> about <hi>An. Mund</hi> 3450 years, as <hi>Daniels</hi> Divine great Calender, <hi>ch.</hi> 8. of 2300 years of their Bondage, under the four Gentile Monarchies declares, (as we ſhall farther by Divine Aſſiſtance manifeſt.) Which, with Chriſts 1000 years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. make up 6750 years, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the little ſpace of Satans looſing, (not ſaid what it will be.) To like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is the concinnitie of <hi>Bucolcerus</hi> in our Table of Chronology in the beginning of our <hi>Irenicon,</hi> of his 50 Jubelies to <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102109:4"/>coming out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and to <hi>Babylons</hi> Captivity 70 Jubelies, which is 3550 years, unto which, part of <hi>Daniels</hi> 2300 years 'till Chriſt, is to be added; and from thence he ſpeaketh as aptly, ſaying, The ſeven Seals, and the ſeven Trumpets out of the ſeventh Seal, and the ſeventh Vial falling under the ſeventh Trumpet, brings us to the ſeventh Millinary, or great Sabbatiſme of the Saints reſt with Chriſt, (as it is called, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9)</p>
               <p>And as God eternally appointed Chriſt (as after may be ſhewed) in that ſtate to be Heir of all thing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his carrying on his three great Works in the world in the 6000 years foregoing (for they alſo paſs through the 6000 to the 7th, wherein he with his Saints ſhall enjoy the ſame, as we ſhall ſhew) the firſt is his making the Worlds, that is, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or his Providencial Management of the ſeveral ſtates of things, 1. in the Old World, 2. in this preſent evil World, and 3dly in the world to come, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.20. &amp; <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. the word is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an habitable world to come. [For as for Chriſts creating Heaven and Earth at firſt out of nothing, ſpoken of <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11, 12. that was his Tranſient act, but this his making the worlds as he carries on his ſaid work of Redemption, through all the ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, againſt the God of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent evil world, and the Children of it both ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of this world, (as the Scripture decyphers them many times as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. and <hi>Luke</hi> 16.8.) ſuch his making of them is his immanent, and ſo long continued act, ſo providentially di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſing what is paſt, and will do ſo for what remains to be done, with the Father and by the operation of the Holy Spirit: and ſo 2dly, for his upholding of all things by the word of his power, <hi>&amp;c. verſe</hi> 3. through all thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or ſeveral ſtates of thing; and 3dly by purging the ſins of his Elect, 1. by his word and will reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 2 by his blood ſhed or to be ſhed, and 3dly, by his Spirit given, through all the ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or Worlds, until from his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal ſecond coming to the Judgment of the great day he perfects the ſaid work of Redemption, and by his carrying on of theſe 3 things in the firſt 6000 years, and that ſo his three fold moſt Juſt Title and Right may then manifeſtly ariſe, of his inheriting all things, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2, 3. which (ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith he) his Saints ſhall alſo then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7.</p>
               <p>But here ſome may object, that the ſixth <hi>Millen.</hi> will ſo want above 200 years, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Chriſt tells us of ſhortning evil times for the Elects ſake: he may mean it of theſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſixth <hi>Millen.</hi> in that reſpect ſeems more like the ſixth day in the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; at the end of which (moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) the Serpent Satan tempted <hi>Eve,</hi> ſhe ſeduced <hi>Adam,</hi> and God in the cool of the day Summons, Arrains, and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenceth all the three ſaid Offenders, and caſt <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> out of Paradiſe: (all which would require ſome conſiderable time) and we know not but that he hath deſigned the little ſpace of Satans looſing to make it up, being a bad ſtate of things with them who ſhall act in that wicked attempt, which yet will not reach the Saints, but only make Chriſt a little work to perfect his ſaid Redemption then, by deſtroying the Devil and wicked men at once, when he laſtly delivers his Saints in the world, as in our ſix Concluſions is ſhewed, <hi>page</hi> 17, 18. of Reſtitut. [alſo a <hi>Germane</hi> Doctor gives an account of much more than 200 years loſt in ſeveral Computations which he mentions, and ſo the 6000 years ſhould be much paſt; (but we inſiſt not upon that) only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowleding God is Sovereign Lord of all times and actings in them; and for ſuch particularities we may not be curious, where he hath not revealed, but we ſee the Parallel of the ſixth day, and ſixth thouſand year from Gods one is conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and (as was ſhewed) we have Gods Spirits Guidance thereto, and Chriſts Explication thereof before the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102109:4"/>ſpace we mentioned: and by all which it may appear there is Scripture ground for Gods Millenniari me for the firſt 6000 years, as well as for Chriſts on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beſides, God appointed Chriſt to be then Heir of all things; ſo the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; manner, &amp; means, with the times for the ſame: and thoſe times arev ery punctually &amp; exactly ſet forth by Chriſt himſelf. We ſhall now proceed to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt irreſiſtable evidence of the ſaid neer approaching time and ſtate.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From Gods eternal Decree mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by his word in four particulars, all to take place in the ſame time and ſtate; all which are alſo Divinely, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and Graciouſly reſolved ultimate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (that none may dare to contradict under a terrible Penalty, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18, 19.) by Chriſt in his Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> to belong to the ſame. The firſt is, his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Decree of appointing Chriſt then to be Heir of all things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. from his 3 fold ſaid right which we but now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, when the world to come, or laſt ſtate of things in it ſhall take place; of which, more (if God will) in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> when the <hi>Revelation</hi> alſo declares Chriſt ſhall have the Sovereignty and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world given to him, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. and all things ſhall be made new for him and his Saints, <hi>ch.</hi> 21.5. to become a fit Inheritance for him and them, as he promiſeth, (as was ſaid) <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. for which purpoſe, when <hi>St. James</hi> ſpeaks of raiſing up <hi>Davids</hi> Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, the Spirit of God directs him to ſet down that great Truth foreknown to God are all his works from the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world] as if he would thereby ſhew that the ſaid raiſing of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of <hi>David</hi> was a matter [foreknown to God from Eteraity <hi>Acts</hi> 15.17. when Chriſt will ariſe and judge the Earth, that he may, (as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh) inherit all Nations, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Gods Word witneſſeth that God made an eternal Covenant with Chriſt to give to him all his Elect in the ſaid times to be redeemed by him, until he receive his Inheritance, and when the Heathen ſhall be given him for his Inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the Earth for his poſſeſſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. And ſo he declares <hi>Eſa.</hi> 62.6. that he will give them for a Covenant of the people; which the <hi>Sep.</hi> very appoſitely and fitly renders
[<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>of my Generation;</hi> not of Bloods, or the will of the fleſh, or the will of Man; but born of God, as <hi>John</hi> 1.13. and born of the Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 3.5, 6. and of this Covenant the Holy Ghoſt gives an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent explication, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59 <hi>ult.</hi> As for me, this my Covenant with them (ſaith the Lord) my ſpirit which is upon thee, [Chriſt] and my words which I have put in thy mouth, (which includes all his Ordinances grounded upon his Word) nor out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed: and again he adds, [ſaith the Lord] (for this Scipture is full of Emphaſis) from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth even for ever: I do here only brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch upon theſe great things, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what remains to future Diſcourſes (if God will) and all thoſe ſo Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Creatures, given by Covenant to Chriſt from Eternity, the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. declares, (where alſo he ſpeaks of other matters reſpecting that ſtate of the 1000 years, <hi>verſe</hi> 19, 20, 21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) that they ſhall be Heirs, and joynt Heirs with Chriſt; and they are alſo ſo explained to be the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down from God out of Heaven, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there, <hi>The Bride, the Lambs Wife,</hi> Rev. 21.2, 9. which will be the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, which before that time were in the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. but then coming with Chriſt at his appearance and Kingdome, are called the Bride the Lambs Wife, at the Saints firſt bodily Reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 5. when as our Saviour prayed, <hi>John</hi> 17.23. they will be then made perfect in one, and behold his glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> verſe 24.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Gods word witneſſeth that God by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102109:5"/>his ſaid Eternal Decree, appointed the Creation of the World for Chriſt and his ſaid Saints, to be poſſeſſed by them in the ſaid ſeventh <hi>Millennium;</hi> for although he made Angels and Men at firſt in the perfection of their Natures, yet he was not then pleaſed to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gage his Almighty Arm to uphold them in that ſtate: wherefore, foreſeeing they would fall, he carries on thereupon his everlaſtitg de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne through Chriſt for his Saints to his own greateſt Glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by whom both the Elect Angels were confirmed in grace and glory; and the ſins of the Saints ſhould through all times be purged away by himſelf; for the good of whom he hath ever ſince made his Elect Angels Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring Spirits, having from Eternity given them by his ſaid Covenant unto Chriſt: Therefore the Spirit of God evidently ſo explains <hi>Pſalm</hi> 8.4. in that excellent E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> chap. 2, 6, 7, 8. ſpeaking by alluſion there to the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam:</hi> but in both texts Chriſt is ſaid to be the Son of Man, which the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was not but only by Creation the Son of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 3. the laſt. And this Son of Man [Chriſt] is he that was for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſeaſon in the world made lower than the Angels, but after Crowned with Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Honour; who for the ſuffering of death, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.) ſat down on the right hand of the Majeſty on high; and hath all things (as he goes on, <hi>v.</hi> 8.) put in ſubjection under his feet; <hi>viz.</hi> Decretively and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, not actually (as all ſhall then be) &amp; ſo the holy Apoſtle ſpeaks there [<hi>we do not yet ſee all things put under him,</hi> v. 8.] and now in ſome ſort or ſence the world is the Saints, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. but then it ſhall be [not only as Chriſt now provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentially orders all for their good therein] but then it ſhall alſo be theirs in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too, at the ſaid times of the Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things (as our Saviour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves in that world to come, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5.7.) Conſider well as to this Head, our Divine Theſes, in <hi>pag.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6, &amp;c. of our firſt <hi>Irenic.</hi> and <hi>Abridg.</hi> p. 7, 8, &amp;c. all (though ſhort) yet of great weight.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Gods word witneſſeth that by an Eeternal Decree he hath appointed to ſet his King Chriſt upon his holy Hill of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Pſal</hi> 2. according to his laſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with <hi>David</hi> for his ſure Mercies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting Chriſts Univerſal and perpetual Kingdome that he promiſed to him for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 7.16. to the end; &amp; that after all the vain attempts in the world to the contrary, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2, 3, which have ever been in acting ſince the Fall, that Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was put by Gods Juſtice between the ſeed of the Woman, and the ſeed of the Serpent, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and will be to that very time when he ſhall come with his Saints to take poſſeſſion of it, which I doubt not but this Generation will ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee; and what a time of trouble will then be, 'till Chriſts ſaid coming ends it, <hi>Dan</hi> 12.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.18. experience will ſoon manifeſt; but notwithſtanding all that hath been, is now in acting, or ſhall be, until then: yet ſaith God, I have ſet my King [Chriſt, the great King of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> as he ſtiles himſelf, <hi>Mat</hi> 5.35.] upon my holy Hill of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> when alſo upon his asking (as he did <hi>John</hi> 17.20.) he will give him the Heathen for his Inheritance, and the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt part of the Earth for his Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and when he will make him his Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne (and ſo Heir to the Kingdome) higher than the Kings of the Earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.27. and Prince of the Kings of the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. and therefore when he deſtroyes the Beaſt and falſe Prophet at the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battel, his Name ſhall be written upon his Veſture, and upon his Thigh; whoſe Name alſo is called the Word of God, <hi>v.</hi> 13. yea, he had a name written that no man knows but he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>v.</hi> 12. but yet, <hi>v.</hi> 16. his Name is ſo written King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, &amp;c. whereupon he with his raiſed Saints ſhall Reign upon Earth 1000 years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 6. which will be Gods ſaid ſetting of his King
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102109:5"/>Chriſt upon his holy Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> and his poſſeſſing of his ſaid Davidical Kingdome for ever, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. which from our 12 Foundations of our Faith hereof is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly evident with others.</p>
               <p>Hence alſo it is very obſervable, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.16, 17. that the Holy Spirit upon the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> his ſpeaking of the raiſing <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle, which the Prophet <hi>Am.</hi> ſhews, <hi>ch.</hi> 9.11. the laſt ſhall be ſo that the people ſhall never more thenceforward be pulled up out of their own Land (as alſo is ſaid 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7) and to be when the fulneſs of the Gentiles ſhall come in, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. which he ſtiles all the Heathen that are called by my name, to which text of <hi>Amos</hi> S. <hi>James</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpoken of the Gentils firſt call, which was in part (as he ſaid by his mouth, <hi>v.</hi> 7. he then adds, after that I will returne, [which words are not in <hi>Amos</hi> 9. but Gods Spirit taught him ſo to explain them] and build up his Tabernacle alſo; and as declaring it not to belong to that firſt call of the Gentiles, but as <hi>Amos</hi> ſaith when all the Heathen ſhall be called by his name; and thereupon adds that great general Divine Truth, here to be eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally applyed to the raiſing of <hi>Davids</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, <hi>v.</hi> 18. known unto God, ſaith he, are all his works from the beginning of the world, as if he would thereby teach Gods people that it was Gods eternal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne then to raiſe <hi>Davids</hi> ſaid Tabernacle in Chriſt according to his Covenant with <hi>David, viz.</hi> for his Houſe, his Throne, and Kingdome for ever, as 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. and that all the works of God in the world ſince tend to fulfil that which is his great deſigne in that time in the world; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for Chriſt to reign in the renewed ſtate thereof with his Saints in it, where they had all been before ſo Conteamed, Perſecuted, and Oppreſſed by the black Prince of this preſent evil world, and by ungodly men alſo called the children thereof; namely of this preſent evil world. And thus we may ſee in all theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, Gods eternal decrees are confirmed and explained by Chriſt as, they ſhall take place in that ſtate in thoſe times ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, of which much more will be manifeſt from the Divine exactneſs, the comprehenſive uſefulneſs, and the certain determination of Chriſt in his ſaid Key, which is chiefly the ſpirit of Propheſie, and the Teſtimony of Jeſus, as he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpoken by his ſpirit in his Prophets, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10.</p>
               <p>The next evidence of the ſaid ſate in the ſaid times, is from the moſt ancient Declarations, Promiſes, and Covenants in his word unto the Fathers, as the next revealed grounds of the ſame. The firſt was Gods own Declaration upon Mans Fall, That the ſeed of the Woman ſhould break the Serpents head; and becauſe he was to be only the ſeed of the Woman, and not of the man, therefore was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily to be the Son of God, as he was manifeſt to be in the in 4000 years after, &amp; by the breaking of the Serpents head by degrees, in reſpect both of his head of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie and Power, at laſt he ſhould ſo make way for his own ſovereignty, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over the Creatures, at laſt to be reſtored to him, as largely is to be ſeen in our Treatiſe on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. ſo that in that firſt Declaration we may obſerve, firſt, how all evil ſhall by him be taken out of the world, <hi>viz.</hi> by Chriſts deſtroying the works of the Devil, as <hi>St John</hi> ſpeaks, and that both in his Deſignes and actings by all his wicked Inſtruments in the old world, and ever ſince in the new world, eſpecially in his deſigns of his three <hi>Babels,</hi> as in <hi>ch.</hi> 5. of our <hi>Iren.</hi> all to come to utter confuſioon at his 2d coming, (having laid the firm foundation thereof by his death at his firſt coming) by bringing in again at laſt oneneſs of Language, peaceable and good Gvernment, and vindicated his Goſpel Truth from Myſtical <hi>Babylons</hi> pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions: but more eſpecially he will break his head of power by his great day of Judgment eminently at the firſt act there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. and totally, and finally at the laſt, <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102109:6"/>
               <p>And 2dly, this in the next place God more generally made known to <hi>Enoch,</hi> as <hi>St. Jude</hi> records it, <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. who was a Type of Chriſts Aſcention, having this Teſtimony, that he pleaſed God, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth (as God was well pleaſed with Chriſt who having done all his wills, aſcended into Heaven, and at his deſcending again begins the firſt act of his Judgment of his ſaid great day, when the body of the Beaſt ſhall be given to the burning flame, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. and the laſt act will totally and finally break h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſaid head of power, which our Saviour teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſhall be after the 1000 years of his Reign with his Sts. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. when Satan ſhall be caſt into the fiery lake, wherein the Beaſt had been 1000 years before.</p>
               <p>The 3d to whom God revealed thoſe Mercies ſo long before was <hi>Noah,</hi> and that three wayes; Firſt, as ſaving his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily by an Ark, from that deſtruction with wicked men by the flood, as a Type of Chriſts ſaving his Saints from the fires of Gods wrath at both thoſe acts of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt men and Devils. And then 2dly, on the other hand for carrying on of Good for the Saints then, God in the ſecond place made a Covenant with <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> for the Worlds and Creatures preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, until thoſe laſt times, and ſet the Rainbow in the clouds as a token thereof, and alſo for the fruitfulneſs thereof, for all their Accommodations till then; and that the greateſt fruitfulneſs ſhould be in that laſt ſtate, as the Prophets afterwards both confirm and explain, as <hi>Joel</hi> 3. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek.</hi> 34. <hi>Amos</hi> 9.13.</p>
               <p>And in the 3d place, God gives a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie to <hi>Noah,</hi> that his two Sons poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> deſcending from <hi>Shem,</hi> who obtained the firſt intereſt in Gods favour then; and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in their time deſcending from <hi>Japhet,</hi> ſhould be perſwaded by God to dwell in the Tents of <hi>Shem. viz.</hi> to be of the true Church, when the <hi>Jews</hi> were caſt off, <hi>Acts</hi> 13 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the two ſtems, out of whoſe roots the Elect ſhould (moſtly) ariſe, until Chriſts ſecond comeing (though (haply) many Proſelites might ſpring out of <hi>Chams</hi> race ſince, as before the flood out of <hi>Cains</hi>) the former Call of the <hi>Gentiles, Hoſ.</hi> 10. is explained <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. and the joynt Call of both to come, is explained, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. when the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> with all Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient people, ſhall rejoyce together, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43. but after that time all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and People ſhall ſee the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the great God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when the Heathen (as was ſaid) ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Chriſt for his Inheritance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.27. all the Kingdome and Dominion, and Greatneſs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome under the whole Heaven <hi>(N. B.)</hi> ſhall be given to the Saints of the moſt high with Chriſt, and all Dominion ſhall ſerve and obey him. And thus briefly of the ſaid Predictions to the ſaid three Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Adam, Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to the ſaid time and ſtate, (as our Saviour hath likewiſe by his <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> reſolved us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Come we now to the Covenanted Mercies made by God to the following Fathers, and their ſpiritnal ſeed, for the Typical <hi>Canaan,</hi> and <hi>Mount Sion</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to enjoy the benefits thereof through their Divine ſeed Chriſt; [for there are many diſterences betwixt them, and their natural races intereſt, which was but conditional, and ſo broken by them, as we ſet down in many diſtinctions, <hi>pag.</hi> 10, 11, 12. of <hi>Reſurect.</hi>] but their ſpiritual Race with themſelves will enjoy their ſure intereſt in the renewed ſtate thereof at the firſt Reſurrection, (as in our Key of the Covenants with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> of which many great things are there obſervable, <hi>pag.</hi> 6, 7, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all ſuiting to Chriſts Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate, and Kingdome of Chriſt, <hi>ch.</hi> 20, &amp; 21, &amp; 22. all holding forth the truth and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, as we more largely ſhewed both in the Syſteme of promiſed Mercies and Covenauts, and the Treatiſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Reſur.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102109:6"/>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful had a ſeven fold gradation of the ſaid Promiſes and Covenants for the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the chief City in it for his natural ſeed in the Type, but as for his own intereſt, he looked for a City that was then a ſar of, at the firſt Reſur. (with his ſpiritual ſeed) that hath foundations, whoſe Maker and Builder is God, which God (ſaith the Apoſtle) had prepared for the Fathers, who Without us alſo ſhall not there be made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10, 16, 40. or perfect in one, <hi>John</hi> 17. in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> as the Lambs Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2, 9. for as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw Chriſts day, firſt and laſt by Faith; ſo it is not to be doubted, but he ſaw that City of an Heavenly excellency, (though it will be in the world then, as our fifteen Reaſons approved by the learned and judicious ſufficiently manifeſt) and ſo the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted Confirmations to the like purpoſe made unto <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob:</hi> as may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly be ſeen in our ſaid Key reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their three Covenants; for here we only briefly touch upon them, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording us their ſtrong evidence to theſe ſaid Divine Truths.</p>
               <p>The laſt is Gods Covenant with <hi>David</hi> as to his ſure Mercies reſpecting his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, gloriouſly to be ſet up in Chriſt, when he ſhall return (as <hi>Luke</hi> 19.) from his Fathers right hand, ceaſing then as Mediator, to ſit upon his Fathers Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. and coming to ſit with his ſaid Saints upon his own Throne then; for all theſe ſaid Fathers natural Off-ſpring were caſt out of the Typical <hi>Canaan</hi> with a ſore deſtruction for their great ſins, <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.10. and <hi>Davids</hi> natural Race cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſucceed him over <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> for the height of their wickedneſs, to the falling of his Tabernacle; for their long bondage of 2300 years, during the four Gentile Monarchies ſucceeding thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (as God revealed to the greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi>) and after his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions is alſo contained in <hi>St. Johns</hi> the beloved Diſciples book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> whenas the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>ch.</hi> 9. and is explained by the Apoſtle <hi>James, Acts</hi> 15. that <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle at the end of the laſt Monarchy (now neer approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) ſhall (as was ſaid) in Chriſt that Son of <hi>David</hi> be ſet up again, when the ſpiritual and Divine part of the laſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with <hi>David</hi> ſhall moſt ſurely be fulfilled, to the exceeding great glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all his ſaid Saints, of his Wiſdome, Power, Juſtice and Truth againſt the Serpent and his ſeed; and of his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Mercy, Goodneſs, Faithfulneſs and Truth to themſelves, as in our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Reſurrection is ſet forth. The like Teſtimony now of the almoſt experienced time God gave by his other Divine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary Miſtical Prophet <hi>Ezeekiel. ch.</hi> 21.26, 27. ſaying both of the fall of <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle in the laſt of his Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Race, I will overturn, overturn, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; &amp; of the raiſing it up again as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The fall is firſt redoubled there not only for certainty of its falling; as the four Monarchies were twice revealed, firſt to a <hi>Gentile,</hi> ſecondly to a <hi>Jew, &amp;c.</hi> but it ſeems to be a farther confirmation of <hi>Daniels</hi> large meaſure of the ſuffering times of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> under the ſame four Monarchies, which by Gods Spirit ſeems expreſsly to be declared in the next words, which declare the raiſing it up again; <hi>viz.</hi> [until he come, whoſe right it is, and I will give it him] which was meant evidently of his ſecond come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for he came the firſt time to ſuffer, not to reign: neither doth God give it to him, until his ſecond coming, at the deſtruction of the Beaſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 13, 14. when the Tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> is to be raiſed up again in him. But this three fold overturning was to be fulfilled in that long interim of their bondage 2300 years, (as ſince hath been found by experience neer to the end thereof.) The firſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturn was by the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> when the <hi>Jews</hi> were led Captive to <hi>Babylon;</hi> [But under the <hi>Medo-perſians,</hi> God wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reduced many of them by working
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102109:7"/>the Spirit of <hi>Cyrus</hi> to it, to fulfil <hi>Jacobs</hi> Propheſie of the comeing of <hi>Shilo,</hi> and <hi>Daniels</hi> 70 weeks, to Chriſts finiſhing tranſgreſſion by his death, and bringing in everlaſting righteouſneſs by his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Aſcention, when God ſet up his Kingdome of the Stone (as was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) yet ſecondly, under the <hi>Greek</hi> Monarchy their Land was ſaddly harraſed and ſpoiled a long time, betwixt the two Wings or Branches thereof, <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Syria</hi> lying on both ſides of it, until the end of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> his outrage, when the <hi>Roman</hi> (by Scripture account) began, under which their Land hath been again greatly overturned, and turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Province until thoſe Ruiners of that Monarchy, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Mahumitans, Sari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> both harraſed it and took it, and by degrees all the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire alſo; ſo that the <hi>Jews</hi> have changed only their Oppreſſors, but not their Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and ſtill in the Land of <hi>Magog,</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, wherein they are to continue in that part until that Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and their preſent Oppreſſor [the <hi>Turk</hi>] both periſh (probably) together at Chriſts ſaid appearance and Kingdom: and thus through all that ſaid time; that three fold overturning will be very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably fulfilled: and the Spirit of Chriſt hath in many things to come alſo witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> as well as <hi>Daniel</hi> (though the Series and order of them is chiefly from <hi>Daniel</hi>) But <hi>Ezekiel</hi> chap. 36. ſpeaks of their Divine Grace as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all future Mercy: ſo <hi>Daniel</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. &amp; ch. 37. of their Deliverance and Union: ſo <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. &amp; chap. 38.39. he had the Viſion of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magogs</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: ſo <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. &amp; chap. 40. to the end of the Book: the Viſion of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Temple upon the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies ſaid ruine: ſo <hi>Daniel</hi> at that end of their dayes ſhall ſtand up in his Lot in that ſtate.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is manifeſt from Gods many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of the ſaid Predictions and promiſed Covenants and Mercies to the Fathers, as they are afterwards confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and explained in the following Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; all which are ultimately determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt in the ſaid ſtate and time, as reſpecting all ſuch ſaid Saints that ſhall then be raiſed by him to reign with him in his ſaid Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatory or Davidical Kingdome in the 1000 years, and be in the <hi>New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> happy ſtate then in the world, at the times of the Reſtit. of all things: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſts ſaid Revelation ought ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly to be regarded and believed, beſides other Reaſons for the light it gives to all ſuch Prophetical Scriptures, &amp; for the manifold comprehenſive uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And here we might proceed farther to ſhew how theſe Covenants were confirmed by the following Prophets which largely might be done, had it not been ſet forth from <hi>Acts</hi> 3. as he ſpake by the mouth of all his holy Prophets, in our <hi>Iren.</hi> ch. 5, 6, 7, 8. and in our 12 ſaid Foundations, with many other parts of our ſaid work, which is now by Divine diſpoſal become a uſeful Comment upon our two laſt Treatiſes on <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. pag. 1, 2, 3, 4. of <hi>Reſtitut.</hi> Since Chriſts Spirit hath vouchſafed theſe great Diſcoveries to ſo weak &amp; unworthy an Inſtrument of late, by the help of all our former Pieces, eſpecially of our more late uſeful Key, and alſo our three firſt Convincing Arguments in the Word Written, abundantly prove the ſame, we need add no more, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and our Saviour, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. applyed divers Texts in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 60, &amp;c. to the time and ſtate of the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> as a pattern of many more, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth Scripture evidence is of the many paſſages in the Goſpels, and Acts, and Epiſtles of the Apoſtles, which receive no full and ſure explication, but by the help of Chriſts ſaid Revelation, which teacheth us alſo, that they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to all the former heads. 1. of Gods eternal Decree in all the ſaid Particulars. 2. To his declared or promiſed Mercies and Covenants afore named; or to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102109:7"/>Prophets Confirmations, Explications or Illuſtrations of the ſame, which all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining their ſence in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and alſo is very evidently the moſt excellent Divine Key of all ſuch Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies referring to that ſaid time and ſtate, and even the Propheſie of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the like, and the partial deliverance of the two Tribes wonderfully by Gods working Divinely upon the ſpirit of <hi>Cyrus</hi> to that end, and <hi>Daniels</hi> 70 Weeks of Years, all ſpecially and immediately reſpecting the Meſſias or Shiloe's firſt comeing. Yet ſince Gods Kingdome of the Stone began, at or about his Aſcention for 1666. years from that his ſpiritual powerful Victory over the Powers of Darkneſs then, <hi>Col.</hi> 15. until his ſaid glorious, viſible &amp; powerful victory be obtained over all his great Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, making them then (at the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) his footſtool: ſo we may thence alſo ſee the drift of that great Foundation then laid for the Saints ſaid Reconciliation to God, was to advance the glorious and bleſſed ends of Chriſts ſecond comeing, when they ſhall reign with him, which we have already given inſtances of, from <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35, 36. explained in <hi>Reſur.</hi> by <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. and of <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained by <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. in the beginning of both our laſt books and ſhall by Gods gracious aſſiſtance do in ſome other of the Epiſtles, but eſpecially as a pattern of all the reſt in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> to manifeſt that Revelation Interpretation of all ſuch ſaid Parts of Scripture is the beſt and moſt ſure Interpretation of them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is manifeſt from the many Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lels in the Books of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> and of the admirable connexion of both: Firſt of the matters and things; and ſecondly of their times or the Series and order of them both. Firſt from their many Parallels: as 1. The manner of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them both, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.19. firſt of the things which both of them had ſeen. 2. of the things then in their own time, as we obſerved in our Summary of <hi>Daniel,</hi> pag. 3, 4, 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And 3dly, of the things that ſhall be afterwards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where many things are ſet down ſuiting to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and though <hi>Daniel</hi> ſet forth more generally and briefly all the four Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. and <hi>chap.</hi> 7. yet at the end of them in both chapters, he ſhews the ſtate of things to be in the 1000 years: at the end of <hi>chap.</hi> 2. he ſets down the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Kingdome of the Stone at <hi>v.</hi> 44, &amp;c. about Chriſts Aſcention, to continue for 1666 years, which ſhould break the Iron <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy in that time, and it ſelf become a Mountain fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the whole Earth, <hi>v.</hi> 35. when the time of the ten Kings, <hi>ch.</hi> 7. and the little Hornes time, time, and halfe a time; <hi>viz.</hi> of the Beaſt or Antichriſt, [haply the Turk alſo, for there are many Reſemblan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of both, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] ſhall be extinct, and therefore in that ioyenth chapter he ſpeaks of the firſt act of the Judgment of the great day to give the body of the Beaſt to the burning flame: when he had alſo the Viſion of Chriſts comeing in the Clouds to receive his univerſal and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Kingdome in the world, next after the Beaſts Date of a time, times, and half a time are out; explained by 42 moneths, and 1260 dayes in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. &amp; briefly in paſſing over the Perſian, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2. and running through much of the Grecian Monarchy in <hi>ch.</hi> 11. to <hi>v.</hi> 36, he comes to the Roman at its height in Chriſts time, and after in the primative Perſecutions, <hi>v.</hi> 36. and to the Popes, <hi>v.</hi> 37, 38, 39. and ſo by the <hi>Saracens</hi> in that time of the end, <hi>v.</hi> 40. and the Turks, <hi>v.</hi> 40. that King of the North, of whom as the ſecond Woe-trumpet he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to ſpeak <hi>v.</hi> 41, 42, 43, 44. to his end 45. about Chriſts appearance; and ſo <hi>ch.</hi> 12. ſetting forth the time of Chriſts appearance and Kingdome, he gives far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther explications of the times of the Beaſt <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6, 7. and thoſe before it, <hi>verſe</hi> 4. and in reference to Chriſts ſaid comeing, <hi>ch.</hi> 10. he had a Viſion aforehand of his glorious perſon, and ſo had St. <hi>John,</hi> ch. 1. and as the man in white Linnen, <hi>ch.</hi> 12. as the great High-prieſt declares the time, <hi>viz.</hi> of that laſt Gentile Monarchy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102109:8"/>ſhould be no longer than Chriſts appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: ſo Chriſt the ſame perſon ſwears the like, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10 at the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet, which is the very ſame time: ſee more in our Parallels of the Roman and Chriſts Monarchy from both Books. And he that is able to make theſe and the like Parallels underſtandingly by Gods Mercy may ſoon prove very judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in matters reſpecting the ſaid happy ſtate of the 1000 years, ſo excellently ſet down by Chriſt farther to explain theſe laſt things in the 4 laſt <hi>ch.</hi> of the <hi>Revel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And 2dly, there is a wonderful connex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of the Miſterious times of <hi>Daniel,</hi> with thoſe of the <hi>Revelation</hi> ſucceeding them, firſt the great Calender of 2300 years in <hi>ch.</hi> 8. of <hi>Daniel,</hi> miſteriouſly given by <hi>Palmoni,</hi> or the ſecret Numberer, as it is opened <hi>v.</hi> 17. by him, at the time of the end the Viſion ſhall be, and <hi>v.</hi> 19. in the laſt end of the indignation, <hi>viz.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Jews; and <hi>v.</hi> 26. as a Key of both, to be ſhut up for many dayes, with many other Reaſons in our Summary on that text, which manifeſt it to be the meaſure of the times of the Gentiles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and Iſraelites and Jews joynt Bondage, which contains <hi>Daniels</hi> three Monarchies paſt, and the Romans to Chriſt, and thence by vulgar account 1700 years to <hi>Rev.</hi> 19 <hi>ch.</hi> as in <hi>Reſtitut.</hi> p. 26, 27, 28. until the ruine of the Beaſt, and until Chriſts ſaid Kingdome of the Mountain begins; likewiſe, in <hi>Daniels</hi> ſecond Number of the 70 weeks, from the execution of the Command, in the 20th year of <hi>Artaxerxes Longimanns,</hi> about <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 3550. to build the City <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> to Chriſts putting an end to ſin by his death, and bringing in everlaſting Righteouſneſs by his Reſurrection and Aſcention, in the middle of <hi>Daniels</hi> laſt week, making up 490 years, when the God of Heaven ſet up the Kingdome of the Stone for its 1666 years, and is alſo the period of Antichriſts Date, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>ult.</hi> to be found out by the Spirits Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdome in <hi>Daniel</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith the apperance of Chriſts come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will deſtroy him, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. and this Number of <hi>Daniel</hi> proceeds i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion with the <hi>Revelation,</hi> from <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> by vulgar account, about 34. by adding the ſaid Divine Number (as I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it) both wayes, 1666. for the end of the Kingdome of the Stone, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning that of the Mountain, as <hi>v.</hi> 35. and alſo the end of the Beaſts Date, and ſo ſtands in connexion with <hi>Daniel</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect both of the former and latter times of <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Revelation,</hi> ſo ſuiting ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably each to other, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For <hi>Daniels</hi> third Miſtical Numbers connexion by a mark [of taking away of Sacrifice, and ſetting up the abomination of deſolation, <hi>chap.</hi> 12.] to be found ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred years after; and yet when it comes after <hi>Adrians</hi> the Emperours dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Jews from ſacrificing about 130 years after Chriſt, and <hi>Conſtantines</hi> about 312. that it ſo wonderfully ſhould be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered about 365 in <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtates time, that by ſuch an eminent hand of God, as we ſhewed. <hi>pag.</hi> 6. of Abridgm. of <hi>Dan.</hi> &amp; of Parral. <hi>p.</hi> 34. it ſhould then be taken away ultimately (as publick at leaſt) to which 365. by adding the before revealed to <hi>Daniel</hi> 1335. (thence to the bleſſed times) the ſaid <hi>Revelation</hi> number of 1700 years, to <hi>ch.</hi> 20. is ſo by that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful connexion made up by both theſe beloved Servants of God and Chriſts ſo ſtrange agreement in witneſſing joyntly to both Divine books from the ſame Holy Spirit, which is one admirable evidence of the ſaid Truth witneſſed by both.</p>
               <p>And as to the excellent Divine Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the Book of <hi>Revelation</hi> in two Schemes, to <hi>ch.</hi> 19. as an explication of <hi>Daniels</hi> ſhort Hints for the Times; during 1666 years, under the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Stone, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.24. from Chriſts Aſcention to his deſcending again, as <hi>pag.</hi> 26, 27. of Reſtitut. with other things obſervable in the order of it: all theſe may be obſerved in our Scheme of Revelation, and Summary of <hi>Daniel</hi> in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102109:8"/>one ſheet, of excellent uſe, (if well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed, and frequently.) But for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the four laſt chapters briefly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. after the fourth Monarchy our Saviour explains Divinely many things as referring to the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, from firſt to laſt, chiefly reſpecting the ſaid antient Predictions &amp; Covenants with wonderful exactneſs, which the latter Prophets, and New Teſtament confirm, as they are ſo explained by Chriſts ſaid <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet many alluſions to other Prophets are made in that whole book to the Old Teſtament Diſpenſations, both of the Camp of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their Wilderneſs condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and when the Temple was built, and to Rulers the 24 Elders; and to Church Guides, the four Beaſts full of Eyes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4. &amp; to <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Viſion, <hi>ch.</hi> 1. &amp; 10. and <hi>Eſ.</hi> 6. to <hi>Zacharies</hi> two Olive Trees, <hi>ch.</hi> 4. the Witneſſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. &amp;c. wherein we may note the paſſing of the handle of Chriſts Key (as we may fitly call it) by Promiſes and Incouragements (as in our ſeventh Convincing Argument) to their times of fulfilling in the 1000 years: as the Souls beheaded, and their fellow Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Brethren, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9, 10, &amp;c. are raiſed to Reign, <hi>ch.</hi> 20.4, 6. which is a very weighty and uſeful conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therein. We only by the Abridgments [mentioned in our Account, <hi>p.</hi> 3.] paſſed <hi>per Saltum</hi> (as we ſaid <hi>pag.</hi> 3. of Reſur.) unto the twentieth <hi>ch.</hi> referring Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans for the former part to <hi>ch.</hi> 19. (now almoſt fulfilled) to Mr. <hi>Medes</hi> Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and <hi>Clavis</hi> chiefly: but the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Decem.</hi> 7. 1664. in the <hi>Prodr.</hi> on Mr. <hi>Durhams</hi> book do explain many things from <hi>ch.</hi> 5. to the end: but note here, that as <hi>Daniels</hi> twelfth <hi>ch.</hi> is a Key to that Book, ſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. to the times of the Beaſts 1660 years, as in our uſeful Obſervations, where that and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excellent matters reſpecting both books are ſet down, Obſerv. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. next after the Tract upon <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. Thus we ſee the Holy Spirit ſo many wayes joyns <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revolation</hi> both in times and things (as was ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) in both Books through the 2300 years of the four ſaid Gentile Monarchies from the falling of <hi>Davids</hi> ſaid Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which points Unto us this conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that God will be mindful of that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant when the time comes: as alſo of all the former whoſe Period is the ſame and their mercie in ſubſtance will be the ſame: and it is no wonder it ſhould be ſo long before that peoples reducement, ſince their Sin was ſo great at firſt, but eſpecially at their laſt and longeſt and ſoreſt Captivity when they had killed the Lord of life with ſo great a curſe upon themſelves and their Children.</p>
               <p>Upon all which ſaid confirmations and evidences Gods Deſign in Chriſts redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was at his firſt coming to be manifeſt to be the ſon of God in the fleſh, and to have a body given him <hi>Heb</hi> 10.5. as in both reſpects foretold by the Prophets, when as God-man he by dying laid the foundation of all future good, Reconciling both Jews and Gentles by his death: <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. and meriting the ſalvation of all his Saints ſouls, about <hi>An. Mun.</hi> 4000. but towards the end of the Sixth millennium at his 2d coming he ſhall powerfully deſtroy his great Viſible enemies and bind Satan the 1000. years and raiſe the Saints bodies from the grave freeing the perſons and outward conditions of his people, and the the world and Creatures in it from the bondage of Corruptions as largly is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained Reſtit. p. 44. 45. 46. &amp;c. and in the 4. laſt <hi>ch.</hi> we ſhall here only farther obſerve Chriſts curious exactneſs that ſpeaking of the beaſts deſtruction at the time of his eminent breaking of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head at the firſt act of the Judgment, he only ſaith theſe are the true ſayings of God c. 19.9. but when he ſpeaks of the promiſed mercies to the Fathers (twice) to be then fulfilled, he ſaith, ch. 21.5. and chap 22.6. theſe words are both faithfull and true.</p>
               <p>And alſo for the times in reſpect of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102109:9"/>when he ſets the mark <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is done, at the renovation of all things, <hi>ch.</hi> 21.6. which before he had ſet, <hi>Chap.</hi> 16, 17. by a like great Voice from the Throne to ſhew their coincidence at the ſame time, ſaying, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is done, as from <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.8. is remarkably explained. [N. B.] page 61, 62. of Reſtitut.</p>
               <p>And for the <hi>quandiù</hi> how long it ſhall continue, Chriſt ſet it down in an unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell'd manner, ſix times over to be 1000 years; &amp; 3 of them abſolutely 1000 years, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and then three times relatively, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thoſe, thoſe, thoſe thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. Firſt, of Satans binding, <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3. 2dly, of the Saints firſt bodily Reſurrection and Reign with Chriſt in the world, <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5. 3dly, of the happy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in that ſtate. 1. They are bleſſed. 2. holy, as the reaſon of that bleſſedneſs. 3. Their ſecurity thereupon, they ſhall not be hurt of the ſecond death. 4. Their great Priviledge, then they ſhall be Prieſts of God and of Chriſt. 5. In their ſupream Authority with Chriſt, then they reigned with Chriſt 1000 years. In ſuch a wonderful glorious manner hath our Saviour determined the ſaid time and ſtate, which is the Divine Millenniariſm of Chriſt ſo exactly and curiouſly ſet before us by his Scriptures of Truth.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, by the comprehenſive uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of this book, it refers to all parts all Holy Scriptures; for firſt, Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains the laſt times of the four Gentile Monarchies, miſtically contained in <hi>Daniel,</hi> as we ſhewed from the beginning of the Kingdome of the Stone, to the end thereof, at ch. 19. whoſe Chronology be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin when <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle fell for the Sins of his natural Race; and thoſe ſaid Gentile Kingdomes reach through the 2300 years of their continuance, to the raiſing of <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle in Chriſt, as the Son of <hi>Davids</hi> Reign with his Saints, New. <hi>Davids</hi> Covenant for his ſaid King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (which that ſtate of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was then grown up unto) carries us back to the former Promiſes and Covenants to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> reſpecting the renewed ſtate of the Land, and the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> belonging to their Spiritual Seed, and <hi>Noahs</hi> Type of the Ark, ſets forth the ſafety of the Saints in the end of the world, by Chriſt their true Ark; the Covenant for all Creatures ſignified by the Rainbow, aſſures the worlds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, and the accommodations of its fruitfulneſs, and that chiefly for thoſe times (as following Prophets teach us) his Propheſie of <hi>Shems</hi> and <hi>Japhets</hi> Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſet forth of what Race moſtly (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Proſelites haply all along) ſhould riſe, as the Prophets after explain in both their double great Calls; and how the Meſſiah from <hi>Adam, Enoch, Noah,</hi> and all the reſt ſhould lineally deſcend, who ſhould reſtore his Saints with himſelf, to a much more glorious and happy Paradiſe of God in that ſaid ſtate and Kingdome of Chriſt than the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had, when he was the only Monarch of the world.</p>
               <p>Yea, this moſt Divine Book will carry us higher than the Creation or beginning of time to Gods eternal Purpoſe in the four ſaid particulars all explained and confirmed in Chriſts <hi>Revelation Key.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the help of this we may judge of the ſeveral Propheſies from the Fountains of them, revealed in the Word of God, as they relate to the Revealed and Promiſed Mercies in their particular drift; as what relates to <hi>Adams,</hi> what to <hi>Noahs,</hi> to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams, Iſaacs</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> for their Land, and what to <hi>Davids,</hi> as to his ſure King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and upon theſe Diſcoveries of Gods ſo giving them title to that ſtate from the ſaid ſure Promiſes &amp; Covenants they will then ſing their Halelujahs upon ſuch accounts, which, the <hi>Revelation</hi> teacheth both us and them; as in our Saints Reſurrection largly.</p>
               <p>Thus we may evidently ſee that what God deſigned to be performed in the four particulars to be found in the 7th Millennium, as Chriſts <hi>Revelation</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts he carryed on in the firſt times by revealed Predictions and Covenants to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102109:9"/>the Fathers, and their Spiritual Seed through Chriſt; which are alſo explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and confirmed by the following Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: all which are wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed to by the Goſpels, and Acts, and Epiſtles of the holy Apoſtles; but laſtly, wonderfully, exactly, and moſt excellently explained and illuſtrated by Chriſts Revelation: and what greater or ſtronger evidence of theſe Divine Truths can be conceived or deſired.</p>
               <p>Now for the ſecond head, what that ſtate is declared to be from the word of God, (for farther we may determine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) which we have ſo largely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the times of Reſtitution of all things, both as to removing of Evils, and conferring of good upon the Saints firſt bodily Reſurrection, which is their inlet into that happy ſtate that we need here add no more, but that Chriſtians ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively peruſe, for that reaſon both our ſaid Books which plainly reſolve the ſame.</p>
               <p>And for the third, to ſhew in a fit lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude the time when, or the neer approach of that ſtate, it was the main drift of the ſaid times of Reſtitution with their neer approach from <hi>p.</hi> 53. to <hi>p.</hi> 71. upon <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. and again to the ſame purpoſe, from <hi>pag.</hi> 73. to <hi>pag.</hi> 77.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe for the fourth, how or by what means Chriſts ſaid Kingdome ſhall be ſet up; not by any worldly means, or any help of man, ſaving by Humiliation, Faith and Prayer, or the like, but only Divinely by the hand of God, only ſuch as are only called by him, <hi>Rev</hi> 19. and <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 149.9. who as he was ſaid to ſet up the Kingdome of the Stone 1666 years before, <hi>Da.</hi> 2.44. which in that time hath and doth, and will in a Divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual way break, <hi>v.</hi> 34.35. &amp; 44, 45. all the adverſe power of the Mettle Kingdomes, which at Chriſts appearance ſhall all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as the Chaffe of the ſummer Threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-flore; ſo God will then give all the Kingdoms of the World unto Chriſt, when he comes in the Clouds of Heaven, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. in the glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and his own glory, and of all his holy Angels, and his Saints ſhall then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Chriſts glory in that ſaid Kingdome which his Father hath given him, as he willed at his death, <hi>John</hi> 17.24. and tells his little little Flock that it is his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers pleaſure to give them the Kingdom, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, for the manifold uſefulneſs, exactneſs and excellency of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Rvelation</hi> in cennexion together, both for their Subject, Matter, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Times, being Divinely Delivered and ordered for ſuch uſes, (as we have ſhewed) and eſpecially in reſpect of Chriſts ſaid Key in the four laſt chapters of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> of which we have ſaid ſo much in our laſt named Book, and in what we have here added to that purpoſe, to prove ſuch a ſtate ſhall be in the world in the ſeventh Millen. that it is not need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful here to ſpeak any thing more thereof. And for a farther example of all we have ſaid, as to the uſefulneſs thereof, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Prophetical Scriptures, we ſhall (as we ſaid) now proceed to ſhow how uſefully and ſurely <hi>Revelation</hi> Interpretation reſolves all paſſages of that nature: We ſhall conſider for a pattern, what we find thereof in that excellent and Divinely perfound Epiſtle of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who were a people ſpecially concerned in that ſtate.</p>
               <p>We come now to give an Inſtance of the great uſefulneſs, &amp; certain exactneſs of <hi>Revelation</hi> Interpretation of all the ſaid Prophetick Scriptures, &amp; of all ſuch paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in the New Teſtament as have refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to any of them; and Chriſts <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> ſometimes in connexion with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> Prophetick Viſions, which appears to me to be an Ordinance of his own holy Spirit for that purpoſe, of which we doubt not but to give a good account, as God may give opportunity.</p>
               <p>But for this moſt excellent Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> a people moſt concerned in that Renewed State of the 1000 years,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102109:10"/>the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> (moſt probably) though to avoid their emulation then, conceals his name; yet being chiefly to write of Chriſts Prophetical Office, then comeing into its eminency, under the New Teſtament, writing to them, takes occaſion to inſert much (as it were by the way) of Chriſts eminent Kingly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the enſuing ſtate; and Chriſt in his <hi>Revelation</hi> very Divinely opens all thoſe, otherwiſe dark, and (by many much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken) paſſages, as alſo he doth many of his own ſpeeches, in the Goſpels that reſpect that time and ſtate, as was eaſie for us to ſhew (if occaſion ſhall require;) and St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this Epiſtle evidently ſhews himſelf to be that perſon rapt up to Heaven to learn ſuch Divine Myſteries in this Epiſtle.</p>
               <p>He begins to Mind them of their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, with others ſucceding, that God hath ſpoken to all ſuch now, by his Son, whom he firſt ſets before them by his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Titles of being the brightneſs of the Fathers glory, and the expreſs character of his perſon, and then what he ſhould be in the iſhue of his proceedings, as God had decreed both for the things, &amp; times, and way, and means to fulfil them, he had appointed him eternally to be heir of all things in the world: it may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that he might well be ſo, for he had made Heaven and Earth at firſt, <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11, 12. yea but that was but his tranſient act before the fall; but he hath three great immanent and long continued act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to paſs through in his Mediatorſhip; [for ſtill the Dominion of the world is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped by the Prince of the Darkneſs of it] and ſo firſt faith the ſecond Verſe farther, he hath made the worlds, <hi>viz.</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſtates, or ſeveral providential diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals; as we opened before: 1. Of the old World. 2. Of the new World. 3. Of the World to come, which he ſpeaks of, <hi>ch.</hi> 2.5. as we ſhall alſo farther ſhew by Divine Aſſiſtance: and alſo 2dly, he by the word of his power upholds all things through all thoſe Worlds, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or ſtates of them; and laſtly purgeth the ſins of his Elect through them all (as was ſaid before) and ſo <hi>v.</hi> 4. and all the chapter to the end, and throughout chapter the ſecond, he magnifies Chriſts Sonſhip by comparing him with the Angels, ſhewing how far, and in how many reſpects the ſacred Scripture ſets up this Son of God above the Angels; he had ſaid ſomething before of his eternal glory for time paſt, but here he illuſtrates his Sonſhip for time preſent &amp; to come: wherein we may obſerve from Scripture ground that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of the learned, of Chriſts being eternally <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the wiſdome in the boſome of the Father, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the word revealed or manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fleſh to be the Son of God, in whoſe face (as being made fleſh, and ſo God-man in one perſon (as ſaith our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) all the Fathers glory is manifeſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. &amp; <hi>John</hi> 1.12, and ſo he is the Fathers only begotten Son at his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, when the Holy Ghoſt overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed the bleſſed Virgin upon her Faith of the Angels Meſſage at his holy concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. and when the fame ſpirit of holineſs with power raiſed him from the the Dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 13. and ſo he is called his firſt begotten from the Dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. for Scripture only ſpeaks of his being the Son of God, only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to ſome Divine Manifeſtation to be made in time towards his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whereby God manifeſts and owns him to be his Son; as he was firſt eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally decreed, or Prophetically declared ſo to be, but no otherwiſe; and ſo at his Baptiſme, <hi>Matthew</hi> 3. and at his Transfiguration, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17. at his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as he prayed, <hi>John</hi> 17. to have as the Fathers Son his former glory, which he had <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo when the Spirit led him into the Wilderneſs to be tempted of the Devil, he brought him to that tryal, If thou be the Son of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mat. 4. And at his Death Gods power was ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt towards him, that the very Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion at that diſcouraging ſtate ſtrongly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts it, Truly (ſaith he) this was the Son of God: And our Apoſtle here adds
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102109:10"/>one more to come, which is the greateſt, the moſt glorious, and gracious accompliſhment of the end of all others before in the world: when he ſhall be brought again into that world to come <hi>[N. B.]</hi> which ſhall, as he there ſhews, not be ſubject to Angels, but to the Son of God: ſo gloriouſly then above all other times before, to manifeſt him to be the Son of God, ad his heir of all things, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that time and ſtate, as his Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, higher than the Kings of the Earth, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 89.27. as we ſhall farther ſhew, as Chriſts <hi>Revelation</hi> Explication manifeſts from <hi>ch.</hi> 2.5. And our Apoſtle from <hi>v.</hi> 4. having laid down many glorious Teſtimonies of holy Scripture for that great Title of Son, <hi>v.</hi> 5. and of his comeing to take his Kingdome at his ſecond comeing, <hi>v.</hi> 6. from <hi>Dan</hi> 7.13, 14. and of his Kingly Dignity, <hi>v.</hi> 8. when Angels are his Miniſtring Spirits, <hi>v.</hi> 7. but then at his ſaid comeing again, his Divine Throne which he ſhall then ſit upon, as the Son of <hi>David</hi> will then gloriouſly manifeſt alſo that he is the Son of God, in that it will be to the end of the world, being then ordered by his Scepter of Righteouſneſs, as <hi>Eſa.</hi> 9. as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained <hi>v.</hi> 9. and the firſt Foundation he laid, for this Kingdome was his creating Heaven and Earth, <hi>v.</hi> 10. and as he made them, he will alſo diſſolve them in his time, <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11. but in the laſt place, Gods ſpirit directs him, <hi>v.</hi> 13. after his Divine man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to point out the time of his ſaid Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Kingdome before ſpoken of, <hi>v.</hi> 2, 6, 8. and that from that great Oracle, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110.1. (ſo often repeated in the New Teſtament) ſhewing it will be at the end of his ſitting there, which is at his ſecond comeing, or when he brings him again into the world, <hi>v.</hi> 6. and in <hi>ch.</hi> 10.13. until then (as he ſhews) he ſits expecting the ſame till that time his foes ſhall be made his footſtool; and <hi>ch.</hi> 2. after he had warned them of hearing God ſpeaking by his Son, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4. as he doth again to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end of the Epiſtle, <hi>ch.</hi> 12.25. he proceeds to ſhew the preheminence of Chriſt in the world to come, which is to begin then, when God ſhall bring his Son again into the world, as he proved before from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97. which <hi>Pſ.</hi> foretels that time &amp; ſtate, and ſhews then will be the world he there ſpeaks of, and tells them, it was not to be ſubject unto An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, but muſt be to the Son of God, <hi>ch.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to that purpoſe then adds a great Teſtimony from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.4. excellently here explained, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7, 8. where he teaches that the Creation at firſt (ſince defaced by mans fall, and Satans Uſurpation and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of Men) which Chriſt had undertaken to reſcue from his Tyranny for himſelf and thoſe which the Father had given him; for which cauſe he was made for a little time low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the Angels, and had made the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of the world anew, which after he was to poſſeſs; but firſt he muſt go to the high Court of Heaven to be gloriouſly put into poſſeſſion in due time, and then to return (as <hi>Luke</hi> 19.) to take his ſaid Inheritance, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom &amp; poſſeſſion, when it is made fit for him at the Renovation of all things, yea for him and his Saints in that time and ſtate here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, as the Apoſtle expreſsly ſaith, <hi>v.</hi> 8. we do not yet ſee all things put under him: but our Saviours <hi>Revelation Key,</hi> in the four laſt chapters, gives an excellent account of that time, and Gods way of performing them; and opens all thoſe things (if men would humbly and conſcientiouſly attend to it:) which I well (through Divine Grace ſtill more and more find doth ſtrongly reſolve all ſuch things above all that man can ſay to the contrary) and ſo as I am well, from his word and holy Spirit, aſſured, he will make good before long time paſs: Now that this world to come is ſo be taken (beſides what was before ſaid) all fitly leading to it, as by Gods Spirit ſo Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely ordered: note farther, <hi>v</hi> 5. it is 1. ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an habitable world: and 2dly, it is ſpoken of to be when God brings his Son again <hi>viz</hi> the ſecond time into the world, <hi>v.</hi> 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Adverb there is joyned with the Verb, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> points it out to be a ſpecial diſtinct time and matter he ſpeaks of, though alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother proof of his Divine Sonſhip becauſe then at his ſecond comeing all the Angels muſt Worſhip him, and it is as was Propheſied of before, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.7. and of that ſtate (which largely might be made thence to appear) the Verb <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, alſo is of future ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on anſwerable to the time and ſtate of that Propheſie, and ſome Fathers, and even ſome Papiſts have ſo underſtead that time, to be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102109:11"/>Chriſts ſecond comeing; of which, much more might be ſaid, but this is to me above all, I am ſure Chriſt explains all theſe in this ſence in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> as our two laſt books (if rightly underſtood) do manifeſt: I thought to have ſpoken of many things more in this Epiſtle ſo ordered by Chriſts holy Spirit, as I find them to this purpoſe, as in <hi>ch</hi> 11. many things of the ſufferers and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> and others; but we have ſpoken of them partly in our <hi>Key,</hi> p. 7, 8, 9, &amp;c and in our ſaid laſt Books: and of the Communion in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtate then, <hi>ch.</hi> 12. which alſo we ſpoke of in the ſaid Books, and more in our Tract on <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. and becauſe we have but a ſhort Introduction in hand to our intended ſhort Scheme (if God will) we will be ſatisfied with thus much at preſent to our preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. The like expoſition I have from Chriſts <hi>Revelation,</hi> of what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of Chriſts firſt comeing, and the firſt Reſurrection of the Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. after he had riſen above 1600 years before, as their firſt fruits, to ſanctifie and effect their Reſurrection afterwards at his ſecond comeing, <hi>v.</hi> 23. and (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>deinde</hi>) intends 1000 years after (as Chriſt teacheth) ſhall be the end, which will be when he ſhall have put down all Rule and Authority and Power, that is chiefly (as Scripture witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth) <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Gog and Magog, and ſhut up Satan in the bottomleſs pit for 1000 years; and after that deſtroy the laſt Gog and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.8, 9. and caſt the Devil into the lake of Fire, and the laſt Enemy, Death, will be deſtroyed, with the Author of it, the firſt Soul Murtherer, and ſin the effect of his wickedneſs, and alſo the matter for death to work upon will be taken away, which are the deſtroying of death, (none remaining from thence in the world in the natural life) but after the ſaid 1000 years ſhall be that Miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the general Rapture, which he ſpeaks of, <hi>v.</hi> 51, 52. at the laſt Trump; at his deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with a ſhout (as alſo the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaks) at his laſt comeing (which I believe from the ſame warrant) he ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 16, &amp;c. as diſtinguiſhing his bringing with him all that ſleep in Jeſus, which he had called the appearance of Chriſt with all his Saints before, <hi>ch.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> from this laſt, when thoſe dead in Chriſt (<hi>viz.</hi> all that departed in 1000 years before) ſhall riſe firſt then, that is, before the wicked at the laſt Trump then: both which ſorts are theſe our Saviour calls the reſt of the dead that roſe not till 1000 years after, or till the 1000 years were finiſhed, <hi>v.</hi> 5. the firſt ſaid Reſurrection of the Saints is <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 5. (as Chriſt there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly diſtinguiſheth both of them) and this may be obſerved by humble and conſcientious ſeekers to be reſolved: which Reſolutions of theſe Texts I do upon good grounds believe ſhortly will be approved by Chriſt himſelf at his comeing, and how matchleſs a Reſolver that <hi>Revelation</hi> (ſo called) with a witneſs is, (and in ſome things with <hi>Daniel</hi> alſo) ſuch as rightly ſeek by it as they ought, I doubt not but may more and more by their own Experience find, and in the interim (after all preſent gainſayings) yet with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared willingneſs to give a Chriſtian-like ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to all ſerious perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) I bleſs and magnifie the holy name of God my heavenly Father in Chriſt my gracious &amp; merciful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, &amp; of the Lord the Spirit my Sanctifier &amp; Teacher (to my great comfort and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction) of theſe and many like Divine Truths (couched as he hath been pleaſed to lay them down in his holy Word) &amp; for others I only here pray, ſaying, Bleſſed and Holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Perſons! in the Unity of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence; open the eyes of thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervants in theſe times, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the holy Scriptures reſpecting that ſaid world to come, at Chriſts ſecond comeing, as our bleſſed Saviour after his Reſurrection o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened his Diſciples underſtandings, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.45. then to ſee the things before, and at his firſt comeing, and eſpecially reſpecting his Death and Refurrection, then newly paſt, &amp;c. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We might here note hat ſtrong confutation might be taken againſt Pelagian, Arminian, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh &amp; Socinian Errours, &amp; many others; &amp; excite all to get true Grace as the beſt ſecurity of all good; &amp; to that end lay aſide worldly &amp; wicked projects in the world, and keep cloſe to God in the uſe of all good means, and that Great Perſons ſhould kiſs the Sun, <hi>&amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 2. but we are forced now only to hint thus much.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:102109:11"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
